Finding Aid for Nomads records.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Nomads records 1965-2011
Nomads Inc.
14 oversize volumes
22 linear feet (in 40 boxes)
2012012 Bb 2
Detroit, Mich. based travel group which toured destinations throughout the world. Records include tour files arranged by destination. These files consist of description of the proposed tour, itineraries of events, and list of tour members. The collection also has organization newsletter Nomad Notes and The Nomad; and photographs from the social activities of the group.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were received from the organization (donor no. 10699 ) in December 2011.
No additions to the collection are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
The Nomads was founded August 1965 by veteran flyer Joseph Benich and Detroit Recorder's Court Judge Joseph A. Gillis Jr. Together with other Detroit area businessmen, Nomads operated as a non-profit corporation. Originally the members shared a common interest in aviation and travel. Membership in the group was limited. Even so, with membership fees, the group was able to purchase an Eastern Airlines DC-7B and begin plans for the Nomads' first trip-New Year's Eve 1965 Fort Lauderdale, Florida. Over the ensuing years, the Nomads would be able to purchase other planes; they would soon be making trips throughout the world.
To publicize upcoming trips to their members, they began a newsletter entitled Nomads Notes, first published in November, 1965. Club member information and other items of interest to the membership were included in this newsletter which eventually grew in size and was commercially printed. Trip proposals and quarterly calendars on separate sheets were included with the mailing of this publication. (These sheets also were mimeographed at first, then printed. January 1983 brought a change in publication format to a slick magazine style which included the trip proposals and quarterly planning calendars as well as several informational pages dealing with club member information. This new format necessitated a name change and thus, The Nomad was born. The reflect changes in scope and style to meet the membership needs over the years.
The Nomads were a thriving organization for four decades. After the turn of the century, with changes in the travel industry and traveler's expectations, the group experienced declining interest, and in 2011 made the decision to disband.
The papers and photographs of the Nomads were initially processed by the organization in the summer of 1989. The collection was gathered from the office records of the Club as well as from the private collections of various members, especially those of Joseph and Anne Marie Benich. Additional items were processed in the spring of 1990 and 1991.
Subjects:
Nomads Inc.; Detroit (Mich.); Tourism.; Travel.; Travelers.
Genre Terms:
CD-ROMs.; Photographs.
- Tours (by destination)
  The records of the individual tours make up the bulk of the Nomads records and included in the Tours series. Organized alphabetically by destination (except for 2007 and 2008 tours), these tour files include tear sheets from The Nomad describing the tour, itineraries of events, and lists of tour members. The inventory lists the files by alphabetically range (Jacksonville -- Kenya, for example). This should be supplemented with the card file (box 36) which provides the tour number, date, whether the tour was in conjunction with another tour destination.
  - Index to destinations (Box 1)
    (see also card file index, box 36)
  - Abaco Island -- Alsace (Box 1)
  - Amazon -- Asheville (Box 2)
  - Aspen -- Bar Harbor (Box 3)
  - Barcelona -- Boothbay Harbor (Box 4)
  - Boston -- Canadian Rockies 1994 (Box 5)
  - Canadian Rockies, 1996-Caribbean 2004 (Box 6)
  - Caribbean 2005 China, 2001 (Box 7)
  - China 2001-Concorde 1985 (Box 8)
  - Concorde 1999 Durango (Box 9)
  - Dutch Waterways -- England (Box 10)
  - Eureka Springs -- Fort Lauderdale (Box 11)
  - France -- Germany 2000 (Box 12)
  - Germany 2001 Grenada, 1997 (Box 13)
  - Grenada 1999 Hershey (Box 14)
  - Hickory -- Ireland 1981 (Box 15)
  - Ireland 1983 Jackson Hole (Box 16)
  - Jacksonville -- Kenya 2001 (Box 17)
  - Kenya 2004 Lisbon, 1996 (Box 18)
  - Lisbon 2002 Martha's Vineyard (Box 19)
  - Martinique -- Montreal 1967 (Box 20)
  - Montreal 1967 New Orleans, 1978 (Box 21)
  - New Orleans 1979 New York, 2003 (Box 22)
  - New York 2003 Orlando (Box 23)
  - Oshkosh -- Pasadena 1997 (Box 24)
  - Pasadena 1997 Portsmouth, 1996 (Box 25)
  - Portsmouth 1996 Quebec City, 1995 (Box 26)
  - Quebec City 1997 St. Charles (Box 27)
  - St. Croix -- Salt Lake City (Box 28)
  - Saint Andres Island -- Santa Barbara (Box 29)
  - Santa Fe -- Scotland 1990 (Box 30)
  - Scotland 1991 South America, 1991 (Box 31)
  - South America 1994 Spain, 2002 (Box 32)
  - Spain 2003 Tucson, 1983 (Box 33)
  - Tucson 1984 Wales (Box 34)
  - Washington DC -- Zurich (Box 35)
  - Card file index (Box 36)
    - Location index (Box 36)
    - 1998-2008 (Box 36)
      (within each year, the cards are arranged by trip number)
- Tours (by date)
  - 2007 completed trips (Box 37)
  - 2007 cancelled trips (Box 37)
  - 2008 completed trips (Box 38)
  - 2008Cancelled trips (Box 38)
  - 2008 Topical files
    - Auditor's annual reports (Box 38)
    - Clubhouse staff (Box 38)
    - Logo merchandise (Box 38)
    - Nomad notes (Box 38)
    - President / Chairman letters (Box 38)
    - Revision forms (Box 38)
    - Socials (open house; Knowmads) (Box 38)
    - Solos (Box 38)
    - Terminal / hanger (Box 38)
    - Trip status (Box 38)
    - Trip offerings (Box 38)
    - Miscellaneous (confirmation cards, brochures) (Box 38)
- Publications
  The Publications series consists of a set of the organization's news magazine, originally titled Nomad Notes, and then The Nomad. This publication dates from 1965 to 2011.
  - Nomad Notes 1965-1972 (Volume 1)
  - Nomad Notes 1973-1979 (Volume 2)
  - Nomad Notes 1980-1982 The Nomad, 1983-1985 (Volume 3)
  - The Nomad 1986-1988 (Volume 4)
  - The Nomad 1989-1991 (Volume 5)
  - The Nomad 1992-1994 (Volume 6)
  - The Nomad 1995-1997 (Volume 7)
  - The Nomad 1998-2000 (Volume 8)
  - The Nomad 2001-2003 (Volume 9)
  - The Nomad 2004-2005 (Volume 10)
  - The Nomad 2006-2011, 12 folders (Box 39)
  - Itinerary booklets May 2009-January 2011, 3 folders (Box 39)
- Visual Materials
  - Anniversary celebrations 1969-2005 (Volume 11)
    (binder includes photographs, programs, and publicity)
  - Photograph album of airplanes and organization members and activities: binder of photographs divided into the following sections: DC-78, Electra, Convair, 727, Buildings, Staff, Awards, Special Activities, Directors (Volume 12)
  - Photograph album from trips 1981-1986 (Volume 13)
  - Photograph album from trips 1987-1990 (Volume 14)
  - Photographs (except where indicated)
    - 1966 Tony Spina, panoramic photograph (Box 40)
    - Pre 1989 Photos (Box 40)
    - 1989 Staff Chili Cook-off (Box 40)
    - 1991 Christmas Brunch, Sir Michigan in Hanger (Box 40)
    - 1991 Clubhouse Maintenance Crew (Box 40)
    - 1991 Star Flyer (Box 40)
    - 1992 Clipper Cruise (Box 40)
    - 1993 Pat Barry Retirement Party, Open House (Box 40)
    - 1993 Clubhouse Damage in Portland (Box 40)
    - 1993 Clubhouse 727-200 (Box 40)
    - 1993 Crystal Harmony Panama Canal, Maui (Box 40)
    - 1994 Board of Directors, Champagne Brunch (Box 40)
    - 1994 SE Asia Encore Group, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia at War Memorial (Box 40)
    - 1995 Board of Directors, "The World Set to Music" (Box 40)
    - 1995 Huatalco (Box 40)
    - 1996 Warren Myers Retirement Party (Box 40)
      (includes roll of film)
    - 1996 Around the World XI, Taj Mahal (Box 40)
    - 1996 Around the World, XII (Encore), Taj Mahal (Box 40)
    - 1996 Around the World, XII (Encore), Bangkok (Box 40)
    - 1997 Christmas Champagne Brunch-Vladimirs (Box 40)
    - 1998 Awards at Detroit Athletic Club, Charity Arrest (Box 40)
    - 1998 Views of Airplane Boeing Super 27 (Box 40)
    - 1998 Around the World Homecoming at Nomads (Box 40)
    - 2000 Flight Attendants (Box 40)
    - 2001 Australia, New Zealand (Box 40)
    - 2004 Joe & Ami Benich, An Evening With, 8/12/2004, VHS cassette (Box 40)
    - 2005 Nomads 40th Anniversary, 8/20/2005 Photos, compact discs (Box 40)